For whom
did I write this presentation?
Of course,
for frontend developers,
for theme authors and
also plugin authors.
And of course for everybody
who's interested in my message.
Because this is a really
technical presentation
we will talk
about languages–
some need
to code is...
Okay. What do I cover
in this presentation?
Of course,
I will talk about
the conformance
levels A and AA.
Because you have
to fulfill them.
I'll talk about techniques
categorized, sorry,
categorized as sufficient
and of HTML and
relevant WordPress functions.
I will not talk about–
oh, I have to rearrange
my second screen,
I will not talk about
other topics,
because I have
not that time
to get the contents
in a basic presentation
about that topic.
I will not cover ARIA,
not CSS or JavaScript,
nor frames– no no,
I have not that time.
But for all the
other topics
you are right here.
Okay. Let's say some
words about me again.
About my, profession–
yes, I am a computer scientist
interested in media
for about, 20 years.
But I am also an expert
for accessibility in the court.
I have impairments:
I am hard of hearing
I am body impaired,
I am a wheelchair user.
And of course,
accessibility in
every topic of my life
was in my interest,
is in my interest.
And so, I got in touch with
web accessibility in 1998,
when I've did my first steps
in HTML programming
with great potential
to create accessible
content for everybody.
But we have to
know how to do it,
and you also can
do it really wrong.
So, I got in touch with
the first WCAG and sort,
we said, at one point,
we were in 1999 I think,
I was a contributor for
the next version of them.
And, today,
I am a consultant
and developer
for accessibility.
Now. What will you get?
A soft warm up,
then a big journey.
We will dive deeply
into some coding.
And I will show you
some user benefits,
how you can create them.
Okay. We'll start with
the soft warmup.
Well, the very first element
of an HTML code is,
of course,
the HTML element.
You know that.
And, that's
also the topic
of my first
rule of thumb.
Define the
page language.
That is also in
Success Criterion 3.1.1
of conformation
level single A,
so you have
to fulfill that
if you want to call
your theme accessible.
It's a very helpful information
for applications,
not for the human,
but for applications
so they don't
have to guess
what is that
human language– no.
If you give them it with
a tag or an element
with an attribute
with a value by lang,
then you have the
application for you,
and they can speak
in the correct language.
Well– how to create one?
You do not have
the language
of the web page–
the human language.
And how to do it right?
You tell the human language
here in the HTML element
with the `lang` attribute.
`lang` is short for language.
And you can see here
an example how to specify
that the human language
of that page is in Portuguese–
Brazilian Portuguese.
But, you know,
WordPress
is a CMS for
the whole world,
we have many
languages,
of course, you cannot
fix that language
because you
do not know
what language the
WordPress administrator
will use.
So, how to do it
more dynamically?
How's that, WordPress,
provides a very useful function
and that's called
the `language_attributes()`.
Put that into
the HTML element
and WordPress will
do the rest for you.
You can set it
and forget it– okay?
Also this language
changes within the content,
content of the
web page.
For example,
we have an abbreviation
in a foreign language,
or you do quote
a foreign person
in the foreign language.
It's very useful,
for a screen reader,
for example,
to tell that page
here comes
another language,
so change the speaker,
for example.
How to do that?
Well, you can also use
the `lang` attribute
in any other
element of HTML,
for example, a `span`
in an inline element.
Or in another block element,
like `blockquote`,
and you can specify
the language change there.
And of course,
you cannot only
specify the language–
you can also specify
the reading direction.
For example,
in English
we use left to
right reading,
and if you want to
quote a text in Arabic,
you [unintelligible]
there is a change of
the reading direction.
And you can do that
with the `dir` attribute.
`dir` is short for direction,
and you can tell property
and [unintelligible]
for other machines
here comes change
of a reading direction.
If you want to go
deeper into that,
then read the
specifications
in ISO 1766
and read that
and you know
how to write
proper language
standards,
language specifications,
like here,
last line short
in this example for
the British English,
for Japanese, and for Farsi,
which is
spoken in Iran.
Now, my second step
here in the warmup
is the page title.
I do not mean the
title of the content,
I mean the title of
the whole web page.
This is the criterion in the
WCAG to help you identify
the web page,
and to give the user
an orientation
within the website
And not only
within the website,
the page title is also
used by search engines
to put the
page title on
the search engine's
results page.
So it's not only useful
for disabled people,
it's useful
for everybody.
What can you
do wrong here?
Well, I saw pages
with no title in it at all;
I saw a page with
an empty title in it,
or web pages
with default text
which it repeated
on every page
in the title element.
Or sometimes I
saw the file name,
or at least there is
no unique title
for each page
in a website.
How to do it properly.
Well, I do see a
list of techniques
you can find them in
the documentation of
the WCAG 2.1
techniques.
Use the title element,
ensure the title element
describes the current page,
and so on.
At least use a
unique title text.
But, you don't know
what the title will be,
because every
administrator,
every editor,
and any contributor,
can write the title.
So, you have to
do it dynamically.
And WordPress again
provides a useful
function for that.
You only need to add
the theme support
of the 'title-tag'
in your theme's setup
in `functions.php`
And in the `header.php`,
you just call the
function `wp_head()`,
and what that will
do that for you.
Why is that possible?
Because `wp_head()`
calls a function
which prints out
the title element
and this function
calls another function
which renders the
document title.
I recommend you
to take a look
in the WordPress
core code
to that function is
quite short [unintelligible]
and it covers every page,
of a website.
For example, a single post,
a search the site page,
or an error page,
not found, and so on.
And you can either,
you can change
the page title,
with filter hooks,
as you can see here,
the `pre_get_document_title`
filter one.
I would
recommend you
take a look at
that function,
it's very useful.
But you also can't forget
that you just use
`add_theme_support( 'title_tag' )`
and the function`wp_head()`.
Okay.
That was a little warm-up...
for you–
I hope you are
in there already.
But now, to try to begin,
we will get deeper into that.
First, think about that,
we have heard that
maybe, before you
started accessibility,
maybe, you learned
about coding
that a web page
is purely
a visual
mouse-controlled interface.
If you have heard
in the other presentation,
you already know–
oh, that is not true,
because when you
say it's "only"
a purely visual
mouse-controlled interface
you already know,
no, that is not true,
because there are
other forms
of presenting
web page content.
In reality, a web page is
a sequence of content
and interactive elements,
controlled by
different technologies
for different ways
of presentation. Yeah?
No. To lay the
ground for that,
a specific mindset
is really helpful.
Just three things
we have to know.
The first is "Text is king."
Because every browser,
every device,
can do with text.
Not every browser
can do with images,
or with videos,
or with audio,
or with an applet,
or with a Flash file.
Every device can
compute text.
Can do something
with text,
so text is king.
If you have
any content,
be sure that
it is also available
in a text
word form.
The rest
is entourage.
The second played
in your mindset is
"Always give structure"
with HTML.
Don't think
about only
the visual attention
of your content.
Separate content
and the design of it.
Mark up the content
with HTML elements.
And I will show
you examples.
And the last, third and last
played in your mindset
is "Keyboard first".
If a web page
is not accessible
with a keyboard,
it is not
accessible at all.
Okay.
Mouse and
loudspeaker and so
are a distance.
Keyboard is the first
which has to work.
Okay, again,
text is king.
Always give structure
with HTML elements,
and keyboard is first.
Okay?
Now you are ready
for the big journey.
Let's take a look at
these big topics:
Structure, meaningful
sequence of the content,
and alternatives for
non-text contents.
Okay, let's go.
When it comes
to structure,
we have to take
closer looks
to three types
of content:
continuous texts,
like you read a paragraph,
headings, headlines,
lists, and so on–
there are forms,
and there are tables.
If you read
continuous text,
I'm sorry,
if you produce
continuous texts
in your theme,
in the editor,
or in your
guidance page,
ensure that
the structure
of the web page
content
and the associations
between distinct
pieces of content
are available in HTML.
Well, if that sounds
a bit abstract
but no going,
I'll show you
some examples.
Bear in mind,
visual formatting
is not sufficient:
again, separate
content and design.
Design, yes, it's okay,
but first is content:
Text is king.
If you want
to give structure,
specify the structure
automatically,
and later you can
design it with CSS.
What can you
do wrong?
Well, just a typical HTML
code with no structure:
There's a div element,
`div` is short for division,
of course, it has an attribute
called `class`
with value `header`,
so we can assume, okay,
it might be the headline,
we have tags,
we have line breaks,
and we have
maybe some type of list?
Yet how we
can read that?
But now,
assistive technology
can't read that,
cannot make sense
about that.
And if you
go farther,
you will see
more examples.
You will see
now a table.
In the
left column,
there are some
type of elements,
and in the
middle column
you see how you
can do it wrong,
and in the
right column
you see how you
do it correct.
If you want to
specify a headline,
yes, of course,
it's larger and bold font
[unintelligible] of the text,
and mostly separated
by a blank line
from the text,
from the paragraph, yes.
But, that
does nothing
an application
can detect,
so instead use
heading element
of HTML
from H1 to H6,
and then you can
design it with CSS.
But then go through
list items for form fields
and for special words,
words like abbreviations,
for emphasis,
and so on.
The last line of the
table tells you why.
Because if you use
another output device,
another than
a visual output,
you lost all
structure information
if you don't give any
structure information.
If you provide any
structure information,
then they will
be preserved
even in a
non-visual output.
Okay?
So, for the
next how-to,
here's an example
for headings.
We have a screenshot
on the left,
of an option page
in the backend.
The red dots are
headings, headlines.
And we can
see them.
If you mark them up,
properly, as headings,
another device,
for example a screen reader,
can detect them
as headlines.
And so blind user
can jump from
headline to headline,
that's a quite
benefit for him.
And you can see here
a visual presentation
of a list
of headlines,
and I think that's
critical, right?
How to: HTML.
Well, how to continuous texts.
Well, in determining
which we have appropriate,
education is when you
know where to look it up.
So, I recommend you look it up
in the specification for HTML:
how to use
the elements,
how to use which
element for what,
and do that properly.
And I can say it again and
mind my pronunciation,
my stress: use them,
use these HTML elements,
and use them and
not other inventions
because with a standard
and maybe other inventions
like division or span
it's not what is known
by other devices.
Well, now we
come to forms.
Forms can really
challenge for users,
with vision impairment,
with mobility impairment,
with cognitive or
other disabilities,
and with others
who are using
assistive technologies.
Oh, forms can be really,
really a burden,
but you can write
accessible forms.
What can you do
wrong with forms?
Well, in HTML, is an
element called `label`,
and the `label` element
provides an association
of the form control,
maybe a checkbox,
and its description.
You can see how
to do it wrong:
you do not provide
any label element or
you provide a label element
but not the association
between the
form control
and its label,
its description.
With these here
two examples,
of label elements
not using properly,
there is
no association
of the text and
the form control
the machine
cannot distinct,
cannot specify
the association.
And in fact there is,
when there are
words the user
have to fill out,
so called,
required fields,
you can see here
an asterisk of form
that there are
form fields
and one form is
required to fill out
and is marked
with an asterisk,
an explanation
of the asterisk
is found down where,
at the bottom of the form,
where that is
not effective.
And sometimes you
see required fields
marked by
color only.
Of course you
can see that,
but can you
hear it?
No, of course not.
Marking by color
is okay,
but that is
not sufficient.
So, how to do it right.
Use the label element
and use other let element
more structural element like
`fieldset` and `legend`,
like`optgroup`
in a selection,
like submit buttons,
especially if you
have selections,
and indicate required
form controls
using labels
or legends.
That means,
in the
second example,
first example is
how to label properly
if you use the
`label` element,
and you use it's
attribute called `for`,
and in the
form control,
you use the
attribute called `id`
and you use
both attributes
the same way you,
and now the machine
or the software can
create an association
between the description
and the form control.
So do can the
screen reader
and other
assistive technology.
Right?
Let's move on
to second example.
How to indicate the
required fields properly.
Well, don't put a
description or explanation
at the end
of the form,
but indicate
an understandable
description
at every
form element
which is required
to fill out.
Or you can use it
in a `legend`
if you have a group
of form elements.
So, and,
then you can
indicate it
with a color,
in the second step,
of course.
First is text is king,
for give structure.
Well, it is
important
when it comes
to backend pages,
or pages for
the backend,
it is really helpful
to provide
a consistent
presentation of forms.
And for that,
it's not,
for that WordPress
provides some functions
[unintelligible] slide,
chapter three line,
`settings_fields()`,
`do_settings_sections()`,
`submit_button()`,
look it up
please to see
the documentation,
and you can prepare
the form with
these two functions
`add_settings_field()`
and `register_setting()`.
You do not have to
write the form element,
WordPress will
do that for you inside,
with these three lines,
and you will get,
and the users will get
a consistent form.
Now tables...oh...
that's pretty important–
if we come to widget
on the widget page,
You can create,
you might prefer,
instances of the widget,
how to be sure that
the ID is unique
on that page.
And for that,
WordPress provides
the two functions
`get_field_id()` and
`get_field_name()`.
Use them, as you
see set in the code,
instead of hard-coded
where you use
these functions,
if your widget
is a subclass
of the WordPress widget
WP_Widget,
you have access
to these two functions
and WordPress
will create
unique ids and
names in the forms
for the whole
widget page.
Okay, now I
come to tables.
Tables are good to
present table informations.
What can you
do wrong?
You are not using `table`,
or the table element–
you are using
the `div` element,
or you are using tables
for visual only,
the so-called layout tables.
And you do not create any
distinction between columns,
headers, and data cells
for example.
So how to tables.
Provide the correct markup,
provide a `summary` attribute,
a `caption` element,
and using ids and header.
I saw an example
how to write it,
in your code,
this is the summary attribute
in a table element,
and here in a complex table
you can see an example
how to use the
attribute headers and ID
so, for example,
a screen reader
can read out if the tables
are with the value 20,
to which column header
the table cell belongs.
Okay. Now, we will come
to a meaningful sequence.
A very helpful
technique.
The meaningful
order of content
means that you have,
the header,
you have the main content,
you have the sidebar,
you have footers.
You can change them
but changing them
will not change
the meaning of
the content, okay?
If that is the case,
then you have
a meaningful sequence.
There might be other,
may be,
several meaningful orders,
of course,
only one is sufficient
for your web page
or for your
theme template.
Yeah? And that is
important because
if you provide
a meaningful sequence
your web page
is accessible
not only in
visual causes,
it's also accessible
in assistive devices.
What can you
do wrong?
Well, you do
not provide
any content
structure via HTML
or you want to
try it with CSS
to at least provide
meaningful sequence
visually,
but again there's
a lack of structure.
That's a big failure.
How to do it.
Use the HTML elements
for structure,
and test your content.
Either turn off the CSS
in your browser,
or else use a
text-only browser
like Lynx, or a service
like Textise,
to have a look,
to have an image
of your text.
Okay?
And now,
the third big step
in our journey,
the third and
last big step,
is about
non-text content.
We all love
non-text content,
like videos,
like audios,
like animations.
But,
text is king, right?
So, what are we doing?
We provide text alternatives
for those types of content.
For example,
for audios and videos,
there's a text transcript
and I will show you
an example in German
of the federal president.
You can see
here a video,
first in sign language,
but then,
the president
starts to talk,
and what he says
is also available here,
as text.
Here as a PDF,
and in an easy language.
So, if you have
a text alternative,
well that's
acceptable, right?
Okay, back to
our presentation.
If you have video,
use captions.
And with the
`track` element,
you can combine video
with captions files,
like so.
If you have `applet`s,
use the `alt` attribute.
If you have `object`s,
use the body of the element
to provide alternative
of the text.
And now, the big topic
is of course, images.
Well, my speakers
before me told a lot
about images and
alternative text.
I just repeat it here.
Use `alt` attributes,
use alt also in images
in sitemaps, no,
not sitemaps,
in image maps.
And if there images
are decorative,
don't use any `alt` text.
I want to provide a
helpful resource
on the server of
the W3.org.
It's the so-called
alt decision tree,
a very funny and
helpful graphic
to tell you how you
write an alternative text.
I know, of course, you can
do it in a quick way,
that was described
in a presentation ago.
There a thought
called a telephone test.
Explain during a phone call
to other person an image
in not more than 10 words–
or maybe 11 words,
or in a short sentence.
How would you do it?
There, you get the
idea of that image.
Very quick and easy
rule of thumb
how to write correct and useful
alternative text for images.
Wah! That's a big journey.
Let's step to the last topic
of my presentation and
you think, well,
I'm running out of time. Right?
So, I will do it fast.
Fasten your seatbelt,
please.
Well, keyboard support
is really crucial,
of course, for accessibility,
keyboard first.
So test your web page
with the keyboard
and without the mouse.
If you can access
all form elements
with the keyboard only,
then you have
an accessible web page.
If you can reach every link
with the keyboard only,
you have an
accessible web page.
What can you do wrong?
You do not use HTML properly,
for example,
here's a `span` element with
the `onclick` attribute.
That is not a link
for a machine,
that's something
what you invented, no.
Or the `onchange` event
on a selection field.
There is not,
there's the
at least two
orientations failure.
How to do it properly.
Well, avoid use of JavaScript
for interactivity and use HTML.
Bypass blocks,
that equate to topic.
Blocks, I do not mean
the Gutenberg blocks.
I mean blocks as
section of your content,
of the web page.
Repeated on multiple pages,
like navigation link block
or the main content block,
or sidebars, and so on.
So, provide links
to that blocks.
These links do not
need to be visible,
the so-called skip links.
If you use,
let me show you an example,
Here you can see
a page of my localhost,
and I am using
now the tab key once
and you can see here,
the skip link.
It's very helpful for users
with visual impairment,
or use screen magnifiers,
and is reading loud for–
is speaking out loud
for screen reader users,
of course.
I use the class `skip-link`
and `screen-reader-text`,
and I recommend you
to take a look
in the file `style.css` of
the Twenty-Twenty theme.
and to re-use
these statements
in CSS for your themes.
Well, we will come
to an end, I promise.
Just links. As we have seen,
in the presentations ago,
provide useful links,
because links can be
read out,
out of context.
Out of the web page context,
for example,
in a link list,
of a screen reader,
or another
assistive technology.
So be sure that
a link text
is understandable
out of context.
What can you do wrong?
Well, using the
`read more` links
especially on
archive pages of a blog.
Then you hear,
read more read more
read more read more,
and you do not know,
okay,
what's the topic
of that link?
Or you use different link
for the same target,
that's okay,
but not for [unintelligible]
because the
lack of consistency
and may cause disorientation.
And now you
open your windows
in new tabs without notice,
for me, I think,
that is not forbidden
but you can do it better.
How to.
Well, provide a link text,
which describes the
purpose of a link.
And uses the same
link text for the same target,
and of course,
use different link text
for different targets
or different web pages.
You can extend the link text
with the title attribute,
but be aware
that is not reliable
because user's screen
can turn off speaking
of the title attribute.
Instead, extend the link text
with visually hidden unique text.
And here you can
see an example of that
I have found that in the
theme Twenty Nineteen
is a function `the_content()`
and you can pass
the link text for that,
for the read more link
and with that construction,
you can offer a link that you
print out only Continue Reading,
but in the assistive technology,
there is a longer description,
a unique link.
Again, then you see,
if you put the title of `the_title()`
into the link description,
and you, so you can
provide unique links hearing,
but visually consistently.
And how to open new tabs.
It's very easy.
Just say in the link that
it is opens in a new tab,
in a new window,
and if you don't like the text,
you can hide it visually
at least it is speak out loud
for screen reader users.
Of course, use a list,
a group of links,
and use an element
`nav` for navigation.
A `nav` element is really useful,
and education, here,
if you know where to look it up.
I provide you a link
because in WordPress 5.5.
there's great support for
nav element using aria labels.
Now I come to the,
I think, the last one.
The last topic
of the presentation,
the focus order.
Focus is when you tab
through the content
and you can reach the links,
the form fields, every one–
provide a meaningful
focus order,
and let me provide
a meaningful sequence,
and so you get a
meaningful focus order.
What can you do wrong?
Use a `tabindex` attribute,
oh, yes, there's
a `tabindex` attribute
that you can control
the order of the focus
while tabbing,
or doing tabbing,
but you do not know
if what it's
possible to–
with other element
without the `tabindex` attribute,
and the other there is
maybe you use
the :hover pseudo-class
for mouse overs,
but do not provide
the :focus class, too.
So, how do you
do it properly?
Use both the :focus
and the :hover class,
pseudo-classes, and avoid
the `tabindex` attribute.
That's my preferred use
no tabindex,
just provide a
meaningful sequence
in the HTML code,
then the focus order
is meaningful too.
Okay, this is
my really last.
We can squeeze something
in not about fooling,
about resizing.
Resizing the window,
for example,
or resizing the content,
with the browser functions.
Well, how can you
do it wrong in HTML?
You provide the `meta` element,
but if you put `name`
–and I have seen that–
you do not allow
any scaling or resizing.
How to do it properly.
A wise technique tells
you don't put it in
or if you have
to use it,
allow scaling
and resizing.
Well, you can see
here in this example.
Well, congratulations!
Now we have
come to an end.
We have learned
the mindset
of a successful
accessible developer.
Text, structure,
and keyboard first.
And we have learned how
to structure the template,
provide a meaningful sequence
without CSS first,
provide text alternatives,
provide skip links,
and provide tabbable
and resizable content.
We have some tools which
helps you in the world,
some data like
Nu HTML Checker or W3.org.
An accessibility checker
online called WAVE,
I love that tool,
and a text only converter,
Textise.
You can find this presentation
on SlideShare now,
on that link, and now,
the line is open for questions.
Thanks so much, Martin.
Unfortunately, we don't
have time for questions.
But there are
some on the site,
and we'll make sure
those get answered.
We're actually
going to be able to
move into
our closing remarks, but...